<entry_list version="1.0">
	<entry id="prove"><ew>prove</ew><subj>LG-vt3a#MA-vt2c#MA-vt3a#PH-vt3a</subj><hw>prove</hw><sound><wav>prove001.wav</wav><wpr>!prUv</wpr></sound><pr>&#712;pr&#252;v</pr><fl>verb</fl><in><if>proved</if></in><in><if>proved</if> <il>or</il> <if>prov*en</if><sound><wav>prove002.wav</wav><wpr>!prU-vun</wpr></sound> <pr>&#712;pr&#252;-v&#601;n, <it>British also</it> &#712;pr&#333;-</pr></in><in><if>prov*ing</if><sound><wav>prove003.wav</wav><wpr>!prU-viN</wpr></sound> <pr>&#712;pr&#252;-vi&#331;</pr></in><et>Middle English, from Anglo-French <it>prover, pruver,</it> from Latin <it>probare</it> to test, prove, from <it>probus</it> good, honest, from <it>pro-</it> for, in favor + <it>-bus</it> (akin to Old English <it>b&#275;on</it> to be) <ma>pro-, be</ma></et><def><vt>transitive verb</vt><date>13th century</date> <sn>1</sn> <ssl>archaic</ssl> <dt>:to learn or find out by experience</dt> <sn>2 a</sn> <dt>:to test the truth, validity, or genuineness of <vi>the exception <it>prove</it><it>s</it> the rule</vi> <vi><it>prove</it> a will at probate</vi></dt>  <sn>b</sn> <dt>:to test the worth or quality of</dt> <sd>specifically</sd> <dt>:to compare against a standard <un>sometimes used with <it>up</it> or <it>out</it></un></dt>  <sn>c</sn> <dt>:to check the correctness of (as an arithmetic result)</dt> <sn>3 a</sn> <dt>:to establish the existence, truth, or validity of (as by evidence or logic) <vi><it>prove</it> a theorem</vi> <vi>the charges were never <it>proved</it> in court</vi></dt>  <sn>b</sn> <dt>:to demonstrate as having a particular quality or worth <vi>the vaccine has been <it>proven</it> effective after years of tests</vi> <vi><it>proved</it> herself a great actress</vi></dt> <sn>4</sn> <dt>:to show (oneself) to be worthy or capable <vi>eager to <it>prove</it> myself in the new job</vi></dt><vt>intransitive verb</vt> <dt>:to turn out especially after trial or test <vi>the new drug <it>proved</it> effective</vi></dt></def><uro><ure>prov*able</ure><sound><wav>prove004.wav</wav><wpr>!prU-vu-bul</wpr></sound> <pr>&#712;pr&#252;-v&#601;-b&#601;l</pr> <fl>adjective</fl></uro><uro><ure>prov*able*ness</ure> <fl>noun</fl></uro><uro><ure>prov*ably</ure><sound><wav>prove005.wav</wav><wpr>!prU-vu-blE</wpr></sound> <pr>-bl&#275;</pr> <fl>adverb</fl></uro><uro><ure>prov*er</ure><sound><wav>prove006.wav</wav><wpr>!prU-vur</wpr></sound> <pr>&#712;pr&#252;-v&#601;r</pr> <fl>noun</fl></uro><pl>usage</pl><pt>The past participle <it>proven,</it> originally the past participle of <it>preve,</it> a Middle English variant of <it>prove</it> that survived in Scotland, has gradually worked its way into standard English over the past three and a half centuries. It seems to have first become established in legal use and to have come only slowly into literary use. Tennyson was one of its earliest frequent users, probably for metrical reasons. It was disapproved by 19th century grammarians, one of whom included it in a list of &#8220;words that are not words.&#8221; Surveys made some 50 or 60 years ago indicated that <it>proved</it> was about four times as frequent as <it>proven.</it> But our evidence from the last 30 or 35 years shows this no longer to be the case. As a past participle <it>proven</it> is now about as frequent as <it>proved</it> in all contexts. As an attributive adjective <vi><it>proved</it> or <it>proven</it> gas reserves</vi> <it>proven</it> is much more common than <it>proved.</it></pt></entry>
	<entry id="prove out"><ew>prove out</ew><hw>prove out</hw><fl>verb</fl><def><vt>intransitive verb</vt><date>1941</date><dt>:to turn out to be satisfactory or as expected</dt></def></entry>
</entry_list>